the our first video in ACE in math
skills to ACE chemistry. The first thing
we're going to talk about is significant
figures, which is one of the biggest
concepts that are going to be used
whether it's an introductory chemistry
like Chem 3A or general chemistry 1.
You're going to be seeing this a lot and
you might have a professor or instructor
that's really going to be trying to make
sure you use these correctly. And that's
because they're very important in
chemistry, in any science class, not
only chemistry. The big reason is it
teaches scientists such as yourself or
future health professionals that we need
to show how inaccurate our measurements
are because we want to be honest. That
is the whole idea about science is that
it needs to be truthful and so that way
we can trust each other as a scientific
community or as a global community for
advancing and for helping those around
us. So when it comes to significant
figures, the big idea here is that well
if I kind of take this one analogy that
I like to use in a lot of my classes and
that is if you remember that famous
scene from the Indiana Jones movie where
he had there's this gold statue in front
of him and all of a sudden he decides to
swap it with this bag that just happens
to be the same weight as it and doesn't
trigger the trap. Well, I mean, in the
movie it still triggers a trap, but the
whole idea is, well, if this is a 20
kilogram statue, well, what what do I
mean by that? Saying 20 kg, what does it
mean? Is it just 20 or is it 20.0 or is
it 20.00?
All these extra zeros, sure, they all
represent 20, but they represent a
different amount of precision that was
used in that measurement. meaning that
it costs a little bit more to get those
extra zeros. So if you're taking the
time to really get those full amount of
significant figures like on the example
on the right hand side up here, well
that's something that you want to show
that right and you want to be honest. So
the whole idea is that all these these
are based on measurements meaning that
we take measurements in the lab whether
it's chemistry biology and a clinic or
pract or like in a more practical
setting we're always taking
measurements. So it's based on whatever
glassear or whatever um scales that
we're using or instrumentation that is
what it's based on. So when we are going
through these, let's say if you take one
of the simplest things that you've done
at some point in your life, which is
most likely you've used a ruler, right?
Whether it's maybe measuring a room or
measuring length of something. The big
thing when it comes to a ruler is that
you might see there's these different
gradients or lines that are on it. And
those different lines, they always
represent tick marks, meaning they tell
you how accur or how precise this ruler
is. And one thing is like if you might
maybe notice is just by looking at this
thing. Well, we have different tick
marks all along this device here. Well,
this represents how precise this ruler
is. Meaning that if I kind of look at
this, well, all right, I can read. All
right, this is 13.1. This is 13.2,
13.3, and all the way up to 13.5.
But if you notice this little red, this
red line that I have right next to it,
well, that's kind of not really falling
on 13.5. Do I just say 13.5? Let's cut
there and be happy. No, you don't want
to do that. Or if you're building
something, someone's going to get really
mad that the measurements are off. So,
you want to make sure that things are
measured properly. So if we look at that
really closely, well this is where
approximations come from with certainty
and uncertainty. So to to summarize that
tick marks, they tell you how certain
you are with your measurement. Meaning
that if I look at this, I was able to
tell for a fact that it was at least up
to 13.5, right? Based on those tick
marks. So these are our certain values.
However, if there is an area where you
fall in the middle or even if you fall
in the line, we always are able to
approximate one digit past that tick
mark. So, meaning in this case, if I
said like, okay, well, I'm going to
approximate that this is at maybe 13.52,
13.53,
any of those values are reasonable
because it's your measurement. You are
the scientist. you can approximate it
however you're seeing it with your eyes
and that's the whole idea here. So these
are all representing significant values
that are whether they're approximate or
they're certain right? So we have
certain approximate or if you want to
say certain and uncertain that's okay
too.
These are all representing significant
digits or significant figures because
you took the time to measure that value
and to show that in your measurement.
So, this is what we're going to be going
into. Measurements dictate how
significant something is. So, when we're
looking at these, this not only does it
indicate how many sigfigs there are, but
they indicate the precision of the
instrument you're using. In this case,
we use a ruler, right? So, whatever
you're using, you need to show that. So,
that way, whoever is seeing your
whatever your results are, they know if
they can trust them or not. And if and
it's not a bad thing if they're not up
to someone's standards. you did the best
that you could with what you had, but
you're being honest. So that way you can
see if you can improve yourself. So the
whole idea here is that when we move
forward is that we're going to go
through a bunch of rules for counting
sigfigs. Meaning that if I go through
that measurement in the past, well,
there were a number of sigfigs there. So
it goes off our first rule. And then
what that says is that all nonzero
digits and zeros that are sandwiched by
nonzero digits are significant. You're
like, "What the hell is he talking
about? What is that?" Well, a nonzero
digit. Well, think of the word non or
not zero. So that's everything that's
like 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9, right? So just
counting with your fingers. So they're
not zero. So all of them are significant
values. Now if these let's say if we
have like one and three and that's
sandwiching a zero the zero is now
significant and that's because it
depends on where zeros are. All sigfigs
are all based on zeros. So we kind of go
up again up to above to that measurement
we took. Well being that all nonzero
digits are significant. What this tells
you is that oh well we have one two
three four significant figures in our
measurement. So, we went to four total
sigfigs. Let's look at more examples and
try to make this a little clearer. So,
if I go back down
and I go to the following examples,
well, I have this rule here, right? All
nonzero digits and zero sandwiched. So,
if I look at the first one, all right,
well, it's 1 2 123.4.
All of these are nonzero numbers. So,
when we count this, right, we have one
sigfig, two sigfigs, three four. So what
is our answer? We have a total of four
sigfigs. But look at the next one. This
zero in the middle, this is referred to
as a sandwiched
zero. And that is because we have ones
on both sides, right? It's a one
sandwich. So if we want to count the
number of sigfigs, we have 1 2 3. So we
have a total of three significant
figures in this calculation. And even
with larger numbers, we can count how
many significant digits are because it
tells you how precise that result is. So
if I look at this next one, right, I can
see we have 1 2 3 4 5 a sandwich zero 6
and seven. So that's also sandwiched. So
we have a total of seven sigfigs, right?
So they are all present. So that's
fantastic, right? So we're just
counting. That's the best part. It's
only a counting tool to make sure that
when eventually when you start doing
math that you have the same number of
sigfigs at the end that you started with
from your measurements. These represent
your least precise value in the end. So
rule number two, trailing zeros are
significant if the number has a decimal
place. So when you put a decimal there,
all of a sudden it gains significance.
But keep in mind, we still have the
rules from earlier.
all zeros they have to be sandwiched
too. So if you don't have a decimal like
let's say here in this case right
there's no there's no decimal place
there. So are those zero significant?
And the answer is no. They're not. It's
just we only have one significant value
here. So does that change that that
number? No. It's still 100, but it's
just telling you that that first digit
is significant. Meaning that it could be
an approximation. It's still the number
100. Those zeros are just placeholders
to tell you, oh, it's it's a big number.
Now, the second I add a decimal to it
and say 100 point and it's that's more
like, no, it's 100 on the dot. That's
how much you need that. Like, let's say
if this was money and we had to say, no,
you owe me $100. That's something that
you're exactly saying it's exactly 100.
So when we count that because of the
decimal place and this a little math
trick that you're going to see sometimes
is that this makes it three sigfigs.
It's showing that that is actually
measured correctly. And the same thing
here on the next example. Well, we still
have that decimal place. So and being
there zeros afterwards, these are
referred to as trailing zeros
when all of a sudden they're after the
decimal. Well, it's still showing that
it's very accurate. Someone took the
time to make sure that you knew that we
had four sigfigs of value. They wanted
you to know this is a good calculation
or sorry, a good measurement.
All right, next one. The last rule. So,
we have the following rule. Rule number
three. For a number smaller than one,
meaning that it starts with 0 something.
So, think of maybe like pennies, for
example. Let's say if you're counting
change and you don't quite have a
dollar. That's what that means. It's
something very tiny. Leading zeros are
only placeholders. So a leading zero is
like the zero up front or it's it's not
an actual nonzero number. It's just a
placeholder. So they're not significant.
Just because it's a tiny number doesn't
automatically make every single number
significant.
But trailing zeros are significant due
to the decimal. So it takes in rule
number two. It kind of combines the two.
So looking at the following one, right,
we can see we have 0.9.
Well, how many sigfigs do I have? We
have two places here, but only one of
them is significant. Only the nine is a
significant value. The zero is just
telling you it's small. So all we have
here is one significant figure value.
Now going to the next one. Well, it's
the same idea here is that we have two
placeholders up front. It's just telling
you it's a small number. So, we start
counting at the first nonzero value. And
being that we have all these trailing
zeros,
these are all significant. So, what does
that tell you is that trailing zeros are
sign or sometimes significant. So these
are always sometimes
depends on the decimal. So if there's a
decimal there then they are leading
zeros are not. Okay. So leading which is
up here are not significant. So if we go
to the next one you can see that we have
a bunch of leading zeros here. Spelled
leading wrong. That's always fun. So
leading zeros
they're just placeholders just telling
you it's small. So we only have one
significant value but four placeholders
that are here. So that's the whole idea
when it comes to significant figures. So
just a kind of quick little recap of
what these different zeros mean is that
all right well we have some a couple
different types here. We have what we
refer to as trailing zeros. So if I have
the 559 0.0
we have some trailing zeros and these
are sometimes significant
in this case. Yes. And that is because
of this decimal here. So that makes it
all of a sudden it is significant
versus the next example.
This one is a big no
right here. And that is because of the
same reason. There's no decimal place
here. So this is also a trailing zero.
Now in this number we have a couple
different types of zeros as well. We
also have leading
zeros up front, right? Are these
significant? And the answer is no.
And then we have sandwiched
which is a yes. So if we go through both
these examples, how many sigfigs do we
have? Well, on the first one, right, we
have the nonzero digits. Then we said
all these trailing zeros are significant
in this case. So we have a total of six
for the first one for the fi for the
5,000 or 55,900 number. And then for the
next one, we have 0.0020.
So where do we start counting? At the
first nonzero value. So we have a total
of five sigfigs. And that's how we do
zeros. And that can be some of the some
of the hardest parts. So the last thing
when it comes to significant figures has
to do with counting. And I know we've
been counting this whole time, but this
has to do with actual counting. So what
I mean is if you count an exact number,
like there's no ifs, ends, or buts. Like
if I count how many pe how many people
maybe are in your house right now and I
say, "Well, there's you. Maybe maybe
your mom and dad. So maybe there's three
of you, right? So there's three people
in this house. There's not three and a
half. There's three, right? If I want to
count how many books there are on your
bookshelf, well maybe you count 20.
Well, there's 20." Or if I have the
example that I have here with my avocado
friend here and it says, "If a farmer
counts 12 avocados, well, how many
significant figures are in that
measurement?" And you're going like,
"Well, Dr. Dan, isn't it just two?"
Like, that's what we've been doing this
whole time. The thing is, it's actually
not two. And you're going to be
wondering why. And that's because it's
an exact number. So, what that means is
that there's an infinite number of
possibilities for the sigfigs. You can
have as many options as possible. And
the whole idea is that this goes
across a few a few different things. And
that's if it's counted, if it's a
formula, or if it's a definition.
Meaning that it's based on however you
as the scientist want to define that
definition. And like if what I mean by
that is, well, if I go back to my
avocados, well, if I say I have 12 of
them, I can say I also have 12.0.
I could also say I have 12.0000
and keep going. And all of these will
have a different number of sigfigs
associated with them. And depending on
how you use it in your calculation, the
whole idea is that it's not going to
affect the calculation because you can
define those number of sigfigs however
you want. So if you can and the idea is
that you want them to be more sigfigs
than your least accurate or least
precise measurement. And that's the
whole idea about sigfigs. So that's
going to be the last part of this
particular video. So stay tuned and I
hope you enjoy the next one. If you have
any questions, feel free to comment in
the section below. Please like and
subscribe. And I hope this video helped.
And I'll see you all in the future.
Thank you so much. I'll see you all
later. Bye.